And we're hoping that with this fleet we
can speed up the pace of of
digitization. And this is particularly
exciting to to me because some of these
books haven't been open like a hundred
years. So there's just a lot of I think
profound Catholic insight that's just
not accessible to people right now. And
as we get into these libraries and we
digitize it, it becomes accessible. It's
incredible. Well, I mean to think when
we digitize a work here in in the hub um
and and I should I should I should
acknowledge that the Alexandria
digitization hub has been in pilot with
the Bontifical O oriental Institute for
over a year now. So they were they were
instrumental in getting the hub off the
ground. What's incredible to me is that
we'll be able to scan a few books a day,
probably probably more than that. And
the minute those books are are finished
scanning and they get processed, the the
contents of those books are made
available to anyone in the world on any
device in their native language
immediately.
>> Good morning, Matthew.
>> Morning.
Um so today what we want to do is we
want to start to kind of unpack some of
the history of Longbeard and and find
out um uh where it kind of all began and
um and you know the the team as it is
now and then some of the uh the bigger
projects as we look into that horizon.
Um so Matthew here we're in Rome. I know
that you were in Rome for for a bit of
time a few years ago and you know have
um you know spent a lot of time in Rome.
Can you share us a little bit the the
origin of Longbeard? How did how did uh
how did the mission start?
>> Well, I mean, I remember pitching
a bunch of the guys, many of whom would
come to join us um in my apartment in
Toronto. Um I didn't really know much
about business at all or
entrepreneurship at the time. I I was
working at the arch dasces of Toronto
and I I started my my uh my career there
working in the office of spiritual
affairs. um we kind of dealt with a lot
of doctrine questions and and canonical
questions and things like that and so
they brought me in to help kind of fix
up the office, help it run a little bit
more efficiently. It was a great
experience and I mean one thing it it
certainly did is made me aware of the
innumerable uh you know doctrinal issues
that the priests have to kind of cover
off and uh and of course you know I've
been a seminarian for a time so I had
some sense of this but I I didn't I
didn't fully appreciate the enormous
demands on them for that. And so when I
was working there we see a lot of calls
sometimes people asking doctrinal
questions, sometimes people putting
complaints, I need an exorcism kind of
kind of questions, you know, stuff all
over the place and you know, we had to
respond and so we had, you know, and
often resulted in us going to primary
sources, right? And then having to
compose an email and respond and this
this ate up a lot of our time as you can
imagine. So that that that's kind of I
think where the genesis of of kind of
the idea of matter started is there's
got to be a more efficient way to do
this. Um
later on I was I moved on to the into
the special projects office and I ran
that for a while and one of the the
tasks I had was was helping um to get
the world and the church to be more an
active kind of dialogue with each other
on on important issues. So I mean one of
the first projects was helping bring
Steenville conferences to Toronto. And
so that was fun because that was you
know how do we engage young people and
you know um and of course Stenville
conferences had been very successful at
that point and and so they they were
trying to do a more effective job of
engaging young people in the dascese. So
bringing student conferences up to
Toronto doesn't seem to make sense that
posed enormous challenges and
particularly like how do we leverage
technology to effect effectively engage
young people and and encourage them to
come and try this thing this new thing
for a lot of them student conferences.
Some of the other events we did we
started something called the Chester in
debate series which was which is trying
to get you know basically topics that
are let's say like atheism modern
atheism and trying to get a dialogue
with the world on about it. I remember
one of the first ones we did was was a
priest of the oratory in Toronto oratory
St. Phil Nerie and he was debating the
head atheist for Canada or something
like that, head of the atheism society,
whatever it was called. And I remember
just loving that debate and I think
exactly like that's what I wish I could
see more of, right? Where we bring our
best, they bring their best and we just
let the ideas go headtohead, right? Um,
so we did a few other events along those
lines and and so I kind of got excited
um at the prospect of of finding
leveraging technologies and using that
because you were using YouTube and
things like that to distribute this
content using technology to help bring
that the the faith into contact direct
contact with the world and and at some
point I realized that this really
required more focused energy and effort.
So that's when I decided it probably is
the time to leave the arch dasces and
and try and focus on this specifically.
And this goes back to the whole pitching
the apartment. So you know I knew some
guys I but I didn't know a lot about you
know technology per se. I was just more
of a user of it and I'd come to
appreciate its its usefulness but I
didn't technically know how to how to
build this stuff. So I pulled together a
bunch of people um most of them were
were in kind of the engineering world um
some in the design space and things and
said hey what if we were to actually
come together and kind of create some
kind of agency in order to help build
technology and it ensures it's used more
effectively for the purposes of
primarily evangelization
and what kind of shocks me at that
meeting is everyone said okay let's do
this so I mean not everyone could leave
you know leave their full-time jobs
right away but everyone kind of started
investing their time and energy into it
so that that's essentially where Lombard
started And um we started initially just
building websites and and technology
platforms uh for Catholic organizations
growingly started in Canada and then
expanded to the US and then eventually
and then eventually spended to Rome and
so I had to do some more consulting work
here and so I I was traveling between
Toronto and Rome you know fairly often
initially that what the client that
actually brought us here initially was a
Gagorian University Foundation which
later on would become a very close uh
partner of ours and then while I was
here I I realized is that there was a
lot of organizations here that needed
the kind of help that basically the
problem we were trying to solve. It was
it was very poignantly made aware to me
that that there was a lot of
opportunities here. there were big
challenges and uh and I realized I was
traveling too much and so eventually it
just it kind of made sense for us to
kind of move move our headquarters here
and so we made that made that decision I
almost like seven years ago now and and
then very soon so when we started doing
some work at the Pontif universities and
other categorizations around the world
and and then eventually um I met uh at
the time Father Michael Journey who was
working at the Dcastaster for integral
human development and he proposed that
the pope
migrants and refugees week is a big
important issue for the pope and
he he let it he let it you know kn know
to me that the pope wants to do more
about this issue and he wants to he
wants to ensure that the effort that's
being that the effort that he's going to
be supporting is is leveraging all the
cutting edge tools possible to ensure
they're as effective as as as as one as
as possible you know be as effective
they could be and and so if him father
Michael Churnney and then father Michael
uh uh Fabio Bajjo now but now both
cardinals um said why don't we work with
you and why don't you come in and help
us set up this technological
infrastructure for the pope's new
migrants refugee section so that was our
that was our first big project working
with the holy sea directly and and it
was a really exciting project I mean in
large part because I just when I when
they asked me in the meeting what would
you you know what would you do if you
were setting technological
infrastructure for for an office how
would you set it up and I and I said
well I mean that's that's not a very
complicated question I mean I Fortune
500 have a pretty typical stack that's
working well. So I proposed you know the
the the typical stack at the time but I
I just kind of back of my mind I was
thinking but this is never going to
happen. I mean you'd have to get
approval from Vatican IT department and
not to say that they wouldn't be excited
about the prospect making some you know
adding some new technologies to stack.
It's complicated right but they said
eventually I got the call and they said
let's do it and and I and I realized
well when the pope's running at running
something right directly that helps a
lot. So, so, so we did we went in there
and we I ended up partnering with Google
on on that project to help bring in this
technological infrastructure to help
facilitate basically help them
collaborate with with parties around the
world to serve the the issue of migrants
and refugees. And
>> and Matthew, what did it do to you to to
come, you know, from from Toronto from
from Canada where, you know, there's a
there's a real high level of of
technological innovation, there's a lot
of and to come to the eternal city
where, you know, at least the reputation
is that things move at a slower pace. um
uh you know the the Vatican has uh this
great vision but times technologically
it's it's often times a little bit
behind. What did what did you what did
you see the church's needs there? What
did it illuminate more clearly for you
>> that I think there's the people that are
here are very eager to do more? I mean
obviously they're all here because they
they care about you know Christ right
and and evangelization and they want to
ensure that Christ is proclaimed to the
four corners of the earth. I I think
that a lot of the problems that the I'll
say the Vatican but merely you know the
holy sea encounters and the other
pontificical universities and stuff are
a lot are very similar challenges that a
lot of old you know even I'd say like
governmental like bureaucracies have
right it's um these technology changes
very frequently which requires a lot of
uh retooling and re-education of of the
staff and and that can sometimes that
can take that kind of change management
can can take a while and so and for some
reasons you know sometimes things just
lose steam right And uh by the time
you've you've trained a staff on one
piece of tech, the next one's out,
right? And because well, what's the
point? So I mean and and I should say
like it's not they weren't all the same.
Some of them were were at different
levels. Um so there are some Vatican,
you know, dasteries that are very
sophisticated in use of technology and
and others which are which are just
starting to understand it. So part of
that I think is just um a lot of that
comes just come down to leadership,
right? How how important does the person
who's in charge of that particular
caster field technology is in order to
serve their mission. So I think it like
mo the last like 10 years it's be it's
become increasingly clear they have to
leverage it more effectively. It's just
how
um so so that that's that's the first
thing is good goodwill good intentions
it's just this this is difficult here as
it would be with any any big
organization. I think the the other part
that's that's a bit kind of complicating
is I mean the Vatican works in a lot of
different languages, right? So, you
know, whenever you're building a tech
platform, you have to start thinking
about okay, how's that platform going to
work, you know, in in uh around the
world, especially when when you're
servicing people different uh different
language groups and so that that's
difficult from like if you have you know
their various offices which are spread
all over the world, right? Now you're
handling change management not just for
Rome, but you're handling change
management globally which is challenging
and then also the users of these
technologies as well. So again, that's
not a a problem that's that's um
non-typical for like a a large Fortune
500 company. Um uh but I would say it's
it is a little bit more if you think of
like a government bureaucracy is a
little bit more rare, right? So I mean
you have the United Nations and
organizations like that which which
reach fairly far, but not many
governments have that unique global of a
challenge. So that just that makes it
just harder, but but it's not
impossible.
>> Wow. So Matthew, so you're you're here
in Rome. you're working with the uh with
with father at the time in the in the
migrant the decade for for integral
human development and specifically with
the migrants and refugee section. Um
you're you're building this
technological infrastructure. When did
um when did you realize you know with
with the with the innovations taking
place in AI with that space you know
making more and more um you know tides
and ripples uh that you felt like oh wow
this is something that I need to you
know then eventually pivot completely
towards. Well, I think like most people,
Hollywood did a good job of priming
priming me for why AI one day could be
really important, right? I think all of
us like with many technologies were just
kind of waiting for the technology to be
further enough along that actually it's
can be practically useful or or be
practically capable of changing the
world. And so I think when we we started
doing some work with Google and I saw
how they were using AI under the hood, I
I got impressed with how they were
leveraging it. But you know it's um
machine learning you know classical
machine learning thoughts that takes you
know you got to be a pro to know how to
do that stuff well right you need lots
of data and I just didn't see any
practical way for it to be leveraged um
yeah at the time
so really was a kind of a
democratization issue right how do we
democratize the technology and make it a
little bit little bit less difficult um
to use and implement and it wasn't
really till dropped I mean that was kind
of the moment for me when I realized wow
okay hang on this this this is
different, right? This AI could be
extremely useful
and and so then then it kind of like it
hearkened back. I mean when I saw it
being used and I found out Catholics
were using it, right? Asking philosopher
more questions, I realized, okay, the
technology is great, but there's
obviously some problems with it that
need to be mitigated. I mean, the
hallucination when it comes to like
church doctrine is a big deal, right? I
mean, you don't want you don't want the
thing making up church doctrine leading
people astray. This is this is about
people's souls. So, the enormity of that
kind of hit me. But then then I then I
thought back to when I was back in, you
know, in the chancery at Derech Diocese,
right? And and and I thought to myself,
man, if I was working at Derech and I
could just ask this chatbot anything and
it it would go to the sources and give
me the answers. I thought, wow, I mean,
that that could be transformative. And
then when I started thinking about,
well, what if what if that could be
available to anyone in the world, right?
This isn't just a tool for priests and
for chancies. This is uh this is
something that in principle anyone could
use. I realized it was worth it was
worth, you know, uh, making a run at it
to see see if we could we could make it
work for for the Catholic Church. And so
we started a was a research project at
the time called Magisterium AI to see
how far we could go and kind of
mitigating the downsides. So h could we
effectively reduce hallucinations? Um,
how do how do we ensure that the answers
that it's producing are aligned, right,
and and are and are relevant? Um, how do
we ensure that there's greater
transparency when when the AI is
generating? I mean right now you know
when you ask chat should be a question
it it'll generate an answer typically
from its you know based on based on it
training data which you know it consists
of I'm sure some church documents but
also you know Reddit posts and things
like that and and so and so you know you
get a Catholic answer it may sound good
right but how do you know how do you
know it's faithful and so that's why for
us when we built matters from we knew
that everything that our AI said has to
be grounded in sources in the same way
perplexity was approaching this in a
very sort manner so so how do we ensure
that everything the AI says is grounded
in in primary sources and and that way
it helps the AI to to ensure that
everything it's saying is aligned
because it has a source to reference and
also for the people um they can have
confidence knowing that what the AI is
saying is true and if and if they don't
if they think something sounds wrong
they can check the source and see why it
said and anyway so that so that that was
like that was that's began the project
and we found that we found that if you
with the right combination of prompt
engineering um you know citations
um and tools that you could for the most
part mitigate hallucinations.
Hallucinations are always a reality, but
you could significantly reduce them. And
that's when we realized when we when we
scaled this out and let it kind of out
into the world and we got great feedback
that this is something worth investing.
>> Wow. And Matthew, can you share a little
bit about the the team that you know the
behind the scenes that's working on
this? When you um when you first
launched Magisterium AI to the public,
how many how many documents uh were was
it sourcing? Well, well, when we
initially released it for kind of
private testing, this is where we were
trying to work with the arch diocese and
candidates and things to test the
project just to make sure. I think we
only had 600. I mean, we we had the big
ones like the catechisms, the
compendiums, the code of Canada law, um,
you know, up the prim some encyclical,
things like that, the stuff that we that
most people would have on their shelves.
And we thought that's a good place to
start. But
>> what was the what was the response like
at first?
>> It was good. I mean um so you know the
short story when it came to when we kind
of like were supposed to be like
privately quietly launching it for the
purpose of expanding the testing group.
The story is at the time um we released
it we end up I ended up agreeing to an
interview with EDTN. I think it was like
News Nightly or something and uh and I
and I said yes um to the interview but
hindsight that that probably was not a
good idea and I should have waited
because after the interview it it went
viral and then we got so much traffic it
actually crashed us and we couldn't get
back up again because we we were
exceeding all the the rate limits of of
the LLM we were using and so we actually
at the time chatbt was the one we were
using under the hood. So we actually had
to go directly to Sam Alman and appeal
for help and and he responded and he he
stepped up pretty quickly to help us out
and and that was that was in large part
thanks to father Philip Laray who's been
a collaborator um on us on Madison since
the very beginning. So I mean I mean
it's it's it's ironic right that if it
wasn't for Sam Alman I don't know if
Madison I would have been here today
because I don't think we would have a
able to get back up at the time they
were very computed. There's only so much
inference compute to them and chatt
exploded and they they weren't expecting
it and so they were they had to kind of
rate limit a lot of people people are
using their API and so for us we weren't
an enterprise client so we weren't going
to get priority. So if he hadn't stepped
in to do that, I I don't think we would
have been able to get up get back online
for I don't know how long. And and
that's what I was really concerned about
is is is we knew we still had a lot more
work to do matter. It wasn't perfect,
but we still felt it was better than
some of the other products have been put
out there that which basically we call a
rappers. You put like a kind of a user
interface on top of chak and you call it
Catholic, but because it wasn't
referencing the primary documents and
things, uh they weren't really dealing
with the hard problems of hallucinations
and and things. And so and so you know
when those apps came out and people
tried them and they hallucinated well it
didn't didn't look good right um and it
was it was kind of damaging for the
Catholic AI ecosystem. So so I I was
because we were trying to move more
slowly and and try and do this right. I
I I was really important to me that we
continued the work and that and so I
think him stepping in had a had a huge
impact.
>> And Matthew, can you um break it down?
How does Magisterium AI differentiate in
in in theory and also in practice with
regards to the other major LLMs and then
also the other Catholic alternatives?
>> Yeah, it's a good it's a good question.
So in large part it just it just comes
down well one to the objectives of the
systems themselves, right? So so chatbt
and Gemini and Claude and and Plexity
their objective function as we say in
the industry. So their purpose is is not
to is not fidelity, right? I they're not
optimizing on those benchmarks and so uh
you know they can often do a good job of
representing church teaching. I think
they're getting very good um at at it at
it nowadays but they're not perfect and
because they don't they don't benchmark
for it. It is one of these areas
especially in like long form
conversations where we start asking
questions about a more obscure church
teaching and things like that is they
they won't have a lot of data on it
necessarily and they will have a
propensity to hallucinate. So so that so
that that's an issue and then there's a
question of what s when they do go for
sources what sources are are they using?
I mean are they using the right sources
or are they just doing a web web search
and you know grabbing stuff from from
from websites and things which sometimes
may work and sometimes it doesn't right
so so that that that's another another
issue um you know and the other is just
I would say I talked about how their
objectives are not fidelity I mean one
of the major problems I think with a lot
of these LLMs is is they're they're more
and more optimizing for user engagement
which one would expect because that's
how they generate revenue and so that
can often lead to this we call sycopancy
right where they're um they're trying to
kind of keep you engaged and therefore
they off this disposition to tell you
what you want to hear which which makes
sense uh in in a lot of use cases but
not not when you're you're quering uh
Catholic church teaching. So, so those
are two reasons. And the other other
primary one where we saw particular
issues was when they were asked
questions about like complex um
documents or um or spiritual resources
that you have you where you can't just
like memorize all all the all the
content and just regurgitate it and make
sense of it. Like a good example would
be the divine office. If someone were to
ask me, I want to pray the divine office
today, JBD, so give me the divine
office. You know, it may have the divine
office in it, it may have trained on it,
right? So it may be in it in it in its
neural net, maybe in its parameters
there, but retrieving it and and and
organizing it and putting it out in a
way that makes sense and is accurate. It
just is not it's not effective at that.
So we realized that a large part of our
work in addition to expanding our
knowledge base relentlessly was about
building these proprietary tools. I
should say specialized tools not
proprietary specialized tools that would
allow the right context to be served to
the models right so if someone did ask
for principal advice or something we're
working on right now a better example
would be the readings of the day for
which is something that's currently in
matteri it it knows it knows the
location of the person it therefore
knows knows the date and therefore it
can select the right readings and make
sure that those readings are provided to
the model and and that way the model has
has the right context and so you know as
users are interacting we become
painfully aware of of all kinds of
different ways. LLMs are just kind of
limited and whenever we we come across
one of those limitations, we we see if
we can we can develop some kind of tool
to ensure to help the LM come to the
right answer. No, that's extraordinary.
And Matthew, in terms of um of
education, like I can imagine the
magisterium AI would be the perfect tool
to accompany students uh teachers
through through a course, through a
classroom, through knowledge base. How
do you see Magisterium AI, you know,
impacting and integrating itself into
the Catholic education model?
Well, I I think we're already starting
to see how AI is being integrated into
the education space. I mean, I think,
you know, I think every teacher is
probably painfully aware of how much
their students are becoming to rely on
AI and and so I don't I don't think that
uh necessarily is a bad thing. I
obviously we don't want um you know,
people kind of outsourcing all their,
you know, critical thinking skills to
large language models. But, but I I
don't think that's I don't think that
that's going to that's how it's going to
play out. I I think in the end what
it'll probably I think people were
curious by by nature and so as long as
we we're presented with the right
questions to ask I think people are
going to ask them and and I think um
outsourcing to an LLM to kind of give
them a give them uh you know to bring
the right context to bear and and um can
be helpful when on a journey and so I
don't think the people's fundamentally I
don't think people's questions are ever
going to stop provided they they're uh
they know the right questions to ask and
so I I think what it'll just do is just
allow people to kind of work through um
a lot more a lot more than they used to
be able to do right when we think like
100 years ago if I had a profound
philosophical question I would have to
hope my priest could cover it off and if
he couldn't I have to go find a
philosopher right which means I probably
have to go to a university and just you
know um or have to go to a library right
and dig through books I mean I mean so
that's a lot of as we say in the
industry friction right it's hard work
to get that answer and to think now
right to think now all I have to do is
go to mastermind ask the question and
then it queries uh more and more almost
everything churches like set said on the
topic retrieves those documents and and
then the AI reads them all and then
presents me an answer with the
citations. That's incredible. That's
incredible. So, I just don't see
long-term how that is is going to truly
hurt him humanity. Again, provided we we
we know why we're meant to exist and
what life's about and therefore we we we
know the right questions to be asking. I
think in the end, it'll just encourage
people to ask more questions and I think
that that actually will will further um
academics. If you were to say to me like
as far as vision goes, how do I think AI
will play an important role in Catholic
education? I think one of the ways that
we're
one of the things that we're kind of
calculating around is um how much value
would there be for a student if they had
like a private tutor, right, that that
could work with them in a very
personalized way to help them learn? And
I think that this is something that the
broader AI community is working on as
well, but we're thinking about it more
kind of like in a in a Catholic
catechical context. And we see a lot of
value there. I mean I mean you think
about catechic classes typically, right?
I mean you get 20 30 40 50 students in
there. And so you know the the teacher
or the priest or whoever is delivering
the religious sister um they have a
curriculum they have to cover and and
then and they try and cover it. They
deliver it the best way they can. But
you know those those a lot of those kids
um I'm sure would really benefit if they
had more kind of personalized
instruction which takes into account
pedagogically how they learn most
optimally, right? And I think that's one
of the the benefits of artificial
intelligence, right? Is that and this
something we're working for as we build
our voice mode. And the idea is that a
student can actually interact with the
with magic via voice and that and then
Madison AI will be given a curriculum be
basically t told to instruct that
student on on the curriculum and then
validate their understanding as as they
work their way through. And what's neat
about that is is that as the interacting
with the student, it learns about them.
It can adapt its pedagogical style and
approach to help the student succeed. So
in that ways you get kind of highly
personalized learning and I think that's
very exciting especially when you think
about places in the world where it's
difficult for them to get access to you
know to to quality teachers um or
priests or catechists and so I think I
think this is a way to kind of
democratize um this this kind of
catechesis and ensure it's it's uh it's
optimized for every student which to me
is exciting
>> that's fantastic and then Matthew you
mentioned um expanding the uh the
Catholic knowledge base and that was
like one of the projects for magisterium
may you can you share how how you're
doing that. What What does that look
like to expand that knowledge base?
>> Well, I mean, initially it was working
with, you know, some of our
collaborators, some of some of them are
priests and and professors to kind of
figure out what is the primary doctrine
that we should be ensuring Madison
referencing. So, you know, that at first
it was very easy, right? I mean, it was
just let's just get all the core dogma
and the fundamental doctrine in there.
And then the question is where do we go
from there? And so, we had kind of two
approaches. One was consulting with
academics and they were sharing with us
what they think is is most important.
The other was just listening to the
users and and and kind of monitoring
what they're asking about and then
evaluating effectively the AI answering
the questions and then determining if we
didn't think that the answer was
sufficient why and was it due to some
lack of understanding of the question or
was it it just didn't have enough
resources and so it was unne it was it
was irritatingly brief
and so and so that's how expanding the
knowledge base you know kind of
developed is one was if we if we had a
question the answer wasn't good need
sources, cool, let's write down, let's
go research, do some research and find
out if there are some sources that can
cover those off. Let's prioritize
digitizing those and adding them to the
knowledge base. And that helped a lot.
And then the other was just talking to
professors um of different, you know,
different kinds moral and and systematic
and and finding out, you know, what are
the what are the key works that would
most inform would be most useful to
users day-to-day. And then of course, we
started considering what would be of use
to researchers later. So anyways, I um
so that and and we realized that every
time we we prioritized and we ingested a
new trove of data, the AI just generally
got better and I I think it it makes
sense. I mean obviously someone asked a
question, the more the more documents it
has to reference, the better the answer,
right? I mean I mean catechism may give
a very concise answer, but if it has,
you know, five or six different answers
and some of those are historical answers
from from previous CAT, it can it can
kind of see a kind of a a a broader way
of of explaining it. And and I think in
some ways that can be useful because
what we often find is some people may
not be content with the answer, right?
So they ask a follow-up question.
They're really asking the same thing but
they're just they need to express a
different way. And so when it has access
to kind of different kinds of
explanations, it we we found that that
really really helped uh helped a lot. So
I mean our our knowledge base you when
we started with 600 it wasn't we knew it
was not sufficient and so we said one of
our main focus our company has to be
basically digitizing the patron church
and that that's that became a secondary
mission of ours. the first mission being
um build and scale Catholic AI uh second
digitizing the patchway of the church.
So, it wasn't really until we got, I
would say, past maybe the 8,000 mark
that we really started noticing a big
difference. When we had 8,000 documents
and, you know, one document would be
like the Ariticon, like, you know, so
some of these docs were were enormous
that we noticed that that the the AI was
pretty good at finding a number of
references to cover off most queries.
And now I think we're over, you know,
approaching 28,000 works and and
hopefully by the end of the summer, uh,
we'll be able to double that. So what
we're looking at now is having the
collective works of all the fathers of
the church, the doctors of the church,
and basically every everything the popes
have said at least um uh pretty
comprehensively for the last 120 years.
And now we're starting to go back into
the more ancient popes to include those
writings as well.
>> Wow. And Matthew um you know working
working on on these very hard problems,
what does it make you even more aware of
in terms of Catholic knowledge? I mean
this continuity, this you know this
universality at the same time. Um, one
of the big challenges that I know that
um, a lot of the other major LLMs are
facing is what is objective truth? What
are you referencing that you know and
having this this incredibly high quality
of of of knowledge of texts that have
been worked on for centuries and
centuries? What does it what does it
bring to bear, you know, what what does
it make even more clear in your eyes
now? Well, I think uh you know the first
thing is
the questions that we may think that
people will have and we had a lot of
expectations what questions people will
have um are not are not necessarily
questions they ask. I mean and that that
was that was pretty shocking to us. We
there's a word for that. We call it the
longtail. And so when we launched
Masteri we we felt fundamental doctrine
should be able to cover. I think it was
because we just figured at least when we
got it started it'd probably be
catechist and teachers and things like
that that' be using Madison
predominantly but then very quickly it
started getting to the high schools and
it was it was incredible how many people
would ask these very personal questions
like here's something going on in my
life what would the church say to me and
this caused a bit of a panic for us
because that required the LLM to kind of
generalize from say first principles to
that particular situation and you know
the early models weren't that
intelligent not I'm saying intelligence
you know in quotation marks
They weren't they weren't very good at
that. They were okay, but they weren't
great. And but they're certainly a lot
better now. And so you one of the one of
the like key challenges was how do we
help the LLM general generalize and and
or or should we even be doing this? I
mean, my initial instinct was this is we
should not be doing this. This is this
is too dangerous. But then I I realized
that the questions are going to keep
coming. They're just not going to come
to us. They're going to take us to CHBT.
And and so how comfortable are we with
that? Right? I mean, do you I mean, at
least we're we're our objective
functions fidelity. We're going to try
to make sure the AI is faithful, whereas
JPD is not going to try, right? It'll do
its best, of course, but it's going to
be wrong a lot more than probably we
would if we could because we're making
concert consorted effort. So, you as
much as as uncomfortable as you know, as
I was with the prospect, I we knew that
we this is something we just going to
have to do. We have to find a way to
accommodate this. And so then we started
trying to think through where's the
greatest trove of of knowledge or
examples of generalization of church
teaching to people's particular
situations or or societal situation
contextual situations and um and
eventually we realized well hang on the
popes that's what the popes do all the
time I mean I mean like they have you
know they have homalies they have
general audiences not just popes
cardinals and things as well. So what we
did is what we just kind of prioritized
gravit getting all the homalies of the
popes and all the general audiences and
we we just um started digitizing it and
that helped a lot. I mean because now we
had you know thousands and thousands of
examples and um and and so that showed
the AI because these you know like a
general audience the cateesis of let's
say Benedict 16th were incredible right?
I mean he's he's taking very complex
documents and things like that and he's
he's distilling them for for people in
in ways they can understand. So when the
AI had access to those distillations and
and can see those patterns, it just
became more effective at at uh at
generaliz. So that's one thing is at the
long tail was was um was was certainly a
surprise. The I think the other um you
know kind of surprising thing to me in
in this project was was just the extent
to which people are comfortable using
technology to facilitate their spiritual
life.
you know, I I I was, you know, I'm a
convert to Catholicism, but I had to,
you know, I was fortunate to be able to
go to seminary and um so I I benefited
from a lot of, you know, personal, you
know, a time with a lot of great
formators and things like that. And and
so a lot of these these spiritual
practices um became kind of second
nature to me because I was I had to do
them by by force of habit. And uh and of
course, you know, when you're in
seminary, um you're kind of your your
life is is kind of built around your
spiritual life. And and so that becomes
something of a rhythm. But when I left
seminary, I I became aware, you know,
secular makes it really hard, right, to
structure your life that way. And and I
think one of the things I've kind of
noticed, I think one of the reasons why
people um like using technology to help
facilitate a spiritual life is is
because, you know, carrying the the
brevery with them, you know, uh on trips
or between meetings is just something
sometimes not practical, right? And they
may be on a cab somewhere, right? And
and they just want to they want to do it
now because now now they have the time.
And so that's just that's a kind of kind
of a kind of a silly example, but um we
rely we realize that that as as long as
people are busy, right, trying to work
and and look out for their family and
and we're going to have to find ways to
help them um to sell their social lives
and frankly technologies can be very
efficient um at doing that. So you uh
listening to our users and and kind of
what um features they want beyond kind
of a chatbot experience to you know um
you know do they want the readings of
the day uh loading in you know common
prayers things like the angelist and
other things people do on a regular
basis what prayers and and things you
know can we add there's there's other
apps that are that are that are doing
this as well but what I'm looking
forward to in the in the future we'll be
launching uh in the fall is
personalization and I think there's an
enormous opportunity here where we can
start to we as we begin to understand a
user user as they ask questions,
interact with the app, um there's an
opportunity for us then to go a little
bit deeper and ask them more questions
and and and and then we start to like
populate like a vector space around each
user, right? Which is kind of like a
contextual space around each user. And
then and then understanding in principle
that all all Catholics were all called
to be saints. So we have some some some
semblance of of of what you need to do
in order to be a saint which is you know
which we get from church teaching. how
can we help kind of personalize how can
we draw down from the knowledge base
right and ensure that the right
spiritual insights and the right prayers
are available um you know to the users
to help them level up their spiritual
lives and this is something we're really
really interested in doing so basically
it's helping the AI to be more p
personally useful to people in their
spiritual journeys
>> well that's extraordinary and Matthew um
looking at the longtail and and having
access in in in some regards to the you
know the most immediate kind pulse of of
of of the of the faithful, you know, the
questions they're asking, the concerns
they might have, the the issues they're
wrestling with. What has that taught you
about the our our m times um and the and
the faithful?
>> Um, a fair bit, I have to say. I mean,
I've been, you know, users are
anonymized in our system on the back
end, so we don't know who's asking what,
but we we do um we do have to monitor
what people are asking, what the answers
to the AIS, uh because we have to make
sure they're answering properly. And so
uh we do on a regular basis you kind of
do audits of and one of the things
that's been interesting is what we do
know that um when a certain question
comes in what generally what region it's
from and that's been fascinating uh to
see what particular questions kind of
predominate a particular region and
sometimes it's surprising I can tell you
the questions that predominate the west
are not the same that that predominate
the east um there are some there's
obviously there's a lot of overlap but
there there are some there's some
differences
>> what are what are those like those
different themes or different kind of
types of issues that they're looking at
or asking questions about
>> well um one thing I I I've noticed um
particularly in in the states is uh
there's a lot of scrupulosity uh for for
some so that's been interesting right I
mean a lot of questions around is this a
mortal sin or a venial sin so that's
been pretty that's been pretty
surprising to me the scale of which that
mag used just for that purpose um yeah
another one um is and this again this is
particularly in the west uh kind of
sexual ual sexual ethics kind of
questions. Um they come up they come up
a fair bit. Um you know even in kind of
very detailed you know situations and
and I think that's very it's very
encouraging. I mean in some ways I think
I find that very refreshing because I
think that I mean especially in our
culture which is hypersexualized right
there's a lot of you know men and women
I think that are struggling with it and
um and you know and and they're they're
entering into relationships and they
want to make sure that they're they're
living those relationships faithfully
and so just trying to understand what
those bounds should be. I think it's so
that's that's been very cool. You know,
I we noticed like in the in the east um
there's a lot more um you know questions
I think more I would say like more
discovery questions and a lot more focus
on saints and and kind of devotional
practices has been those tend to be
pretty a much larger kind of focus. Um
so anyways these these there's a lot
more I could say on that but uh but
certainly certainly there there are
differences. I mean the other thing I'll
I'll just say
another it's been interesting just kind
of observing the questions that that
that people ask is that some questions
are are not directly covered by the the
magisterium formally.
So we had a question just to give you an
example talking about Reiki which is
some kind of new new age new age
religion um which I I didn't really know
much about. I think I'd heard it before.
And and so when someone asked about
this, they were unhappy with the answer
because it was kind of very vague and
not very helpful. And so we were like we
looked into it as we do typically when
when we have a problem with an answer
and said, "Well, why did what's why the
AI why did the AI come up short on this
one?" And what we we've realized is
because the church has never formally
had I never formally addressed that at
least at at the the Holy C Vatican
level, but it had been addressed at the
conference level by the USCCCB.
So, so that was a that was a good
example of, you know, we started
primarily with kind of official church
teaching at the at the highest and we
realized that that we also have to
embrace kind of more local church
teaching too from the conference. And
this is something that we're becoming
more and more um focused on now is is
working with the bishop's conferences to
determine what documents and what
important spiritual context do they
think needs the model needs to have
access to so that people that are using
Madison in their regions are getting
answers which are not just universally
relevant but are also you know
particularly relevant to them right
they're taking into account um local
customs and and and and kind of local
doctrine and and that's not that's not
because doctrine would would obviously
deviate from magisterial but simply it's
just been better explained or emphasized
in important ways. And I think this this
Raiki was was a was a good example. The
USB had a pretty substantial document
explaining why that that that practice
is is dubious. And so anyways, as as as
you ask these questions, when we become
aware of that there are still gaps in
our knowledge base, it then allows us to
kind of start an investigation to find
out who's covered it off. And sometimes
it's it can be surprising um where those
answers come from.
>> No, that that's that's fascinating. And
Matthew, um, as we as we look forward in
like the next six months, the next year,
um, what what developments are gonna
should users look out for on Magisterium
AI in terms of of things that are coming
up? Um, the users I know that there are
many users who use it on a daily basis,
some use it for classroom, some are
using it for formation, but what are
what are things that you're excited
about that are coming up?
>> Well, I mean, one just would be this the
is getting better. I mean, a lot better.
So we got to get smarter. So more
intelligent um better at answering your
question
hopefully um you know clearly and and
and concisely uh but certainly it'll get
better and then and that's because you
know as a company we're committed to
being AI complete and that means as new
state-of-the-art models come out we
always want to take advantage of of the
most intelligent models and make sure
that they're powering Madagascar under
the hood. That comes with particular
challenges. Every time a new model comes
out, we have to effectively evaluate um
how faithful it is and and so we that's
why we developed these these eval which
is a a short form for evaluations. It's
basically a a long list of question and
answer pairs. Some of those are informed
by our user our users and and what we
have to do is we have to kind of run
those questions by the model and see how
it answers and see how well it
represents church teaching. And what we
often find is sometimes it doesn't in
some ways. And so then we have to kind
of figure out can we mitigate this
problem like we did in the early days
right with this particular model. And if
we can then um then we may swap the
model out under the hood and then we can
use that more state-of-the-art model.
And and and that's enormously beneficial
because it just allows it to I mean
especially with re more reasoning
breakthroughs in these models as they
get better and better reasoning. It just
means that they're better able to
generalize church teaching in people's
lives and things like that or or make
better better you know reading
suggestions and things like that. So
that's one thing I'm excited about just
generally is is uh is is seeing how
these how the new breakthroughs and
generally in the AI industry we can
actually make them you know uh
practically useful to the faithful
within Madison. So that's one. The other
thing is of course the knowledge base
expanding. I mean I'm super excited
about that. We're just I'm here in Rome
right now because we're standing up the
Alexandria digitization hub which is
basically an effort with with the
Pontipical Gregorian University. What
we're doing is we recognize that we need
to expand the Catholic data set. I mean,
we don't have uh we don't have nearly
enough like and and if if we're going to
continue to work on um training our own
models, which which is we're doing, I
haven't talked about this, but Ephraim,
which is the world's first Catholic
language model, is something that we we
trained um just at the end of last year,
and now we're just finished finishing a
a new training run on 2.0. We haven't
released it to the public, but we're
seeing very promising signs that um that
you can train a model to be faithful.
So, uh but in order to do that
effectively, we need more and more data.
And so then the question, you know, how
do we get more data? Where's that data?
And we realized that that data was in
the libraries for the most part. And so
the question was then how do we get that
that data out? And so we we realized
that we we have to get to the books. We
have to find ways to digitize the books.
We need to scale up that digitization
operation because there's not much of it
going on here in Rome. So we realized we
needed to to get to get uh to speed up
the pace of digitization. And we needed
tools um like vulgate AI which we built
to help extract the information and col
you know and process it and then uh
convert to vector embeddings which makes
it kind of language agnostic and allows
people to query the knowledge in any
language and derive insights. Um we
needed we needed to further develop that
technology. Um and so so with this
Alexandria digitization hub here in Rome
um we have these robot scanners which
which is really cool. I mean, you put
put a book down and the robot literally
like turns the page, scans it, turns the
page and scans it. We bought a little
fleet of these and we're hoping that
with this fleet, we can speed up the
pace of of digitization. And this is
particularly exciting to to me because
some of these books haven't been open
like 100 years. So, there's just a lot
of I think profound Catholic insight
that's just not accessible to people
right now. And as we get into these
libraries and we digitize it, it becomes
accessible. It's incredible. Well, I
mean, think when we digitize a work here
in in the hub. Um, and and I should I
should I should acknowledge that the
Alexandria Digitation Hub has been in
pilot with the Bontific or Oriental
Institute for over a year now. So, they
were they were instrumental in getting
the hub off the ground. What's
incredible to me is that we'll be able
to scan a few books a day, probably
probably more than that. And the minute
those books are are finished scanning
and they get processed, the the contents
of those books are made available to
anyone in the world on any device in
their native language immediately. It it
it's in it's it's incredible to me. So,
you know, pretty soon everything the
church has ever written will be
available to anyone on any device in
their native language, right? I mean,
this just it's insane. So, and you think
about like you have an AI which is
becoming something like of a master
apologist, right? and he and he has
perfectly has access to the entirety of
everything's been written and all of
that is distilled for you when you ask a
question. I mean, so never before never
before have we had this and I think it's
an enormous opportunity for
evangelization. This is not to say that
the important roles of of of
you know the evangelist, you know, the
human is is is unimportant. It totally
is important. But there's I think
there's going to be a lot of people that
are going to be starting journeys to the
Catholic faith. And I I don't think I
think everyone acknowledge we don't have
enough priests and we do not have enough
lay evangelists. And so we need to make
sure that people when they have these
profound questions that they can get
good faithful answers. And so I think
you know AI is is not a perfect solution
and it's not an end of itself but it
certainly is a really powerful means to
start people on a journey right to get
get them answers to profound questions
and hopefully that'll start them on a
journey which eventually leads to them
uh making contact with a a Christian
community or or or a priest. So the
knowledge base expanding because of the
you know because of things like the hub
and vulgate is is uh is super exciting
to me and I I think it's going to not
just affect um evangelization which I
think it'll also al actually help with
academic research uh in in really
important ways as well because as I said
as we digitize these books and when a
researcher types in a question they may
uh we're already finding this now they
may be shocked to see what kind of comes
up they weren't even aware that these
books exist and then you know therefore
they're able to dig into them and they
may find you know more interesting
research church areas or so. So so
that's that's an important one. Another
tech uh technology we'll be rolling out
soon or should say feature which I'm
really excited about is something called
saint chat which you know as you might
have guessed is the ability to chat
directly with a saint and and I know
that the concept of this has been around
for a while but we think we're we think
we're really well positioned to do a
good job with this because we have have
digitized the collective works of the
respective saint. I mean that that's so
that's that that takes you so far,
right? So if you ask a question of the
saint well at least at least the or the
I should say this the saint AI
in principle having access to its work
is is useful but that doesn't tell you
about you know the saint's personality
right I mean what were they like to deal
with and interact with you know what was
what was truly special about their
presence um what kind of impact did they
have on the world what was their lasting
legacy their works aren't going to tell
you that right you need context context
for that and so one of the things that's
been really neat as we go and and
digitize um all all the all the papal
reflections and things like that
throughout the years and from other
saints. The saints reflect on other
saints. They provide context on their
lives, right? Sometimes what it was like
to interact with them or sometimes
reflecting on them spiritually in their
writings. Same thing with the popes. And
so if you take their writings and you
take all the context on the saints,
right, along with biographical
information, you put that all together
as context um for the AI, it can do an
incredible job impersonating a saint.
So, and I think like if you don't do all
that, right, you're not truly you're not
truly going to be having, I think, like
a saint chat experience, which is which
is truly authentic and useful. So,
that's something I'm really looking
forward to that that'll be launching in
the next couple months.
>> And Matthew, can can you share with us
some of the some of the potential saints
that that people could be interacting?
>> Well, I mean, think doctors of the
church. I mean, so all the big ones,
Kathn of Sienna, Theresa Villa, you
know, uh, some, you know, we'll have
well, some of the more not saints, but
Ben 16, some of the more notable, uh,
popes, uh, John Paul II will certainly
will certainly be in there as well. St.
Thomas Aquinas, St. Augustine.
>> That's very exciting.
>> And, and I just want to, you know, let
me riff, if you don't mind, give me one
more moment on this because I, this is
one part of the St. I'm really excited
about is it's we thought about when we
were going through and thinking through
this app. You know, it's talking to a
saint is fun, but imagine you could get
one saint to talk to another saint. And
we were like, "Oh, that'd be that'd be
interesting, right?" So then we're so
then we were like, so what if we created
like this debate kind of mode where you
could get like one saint to debate
another saint or discuss doesn't have to
be a debate on a on a on a topic, right?
So it be like let's have Edith Stein
debate Katherine of Sienna. I don't know
on on the importance of of lay women in
society or something like that, right?
Or on the lay on the lay on the way the
lay woman vocation and then you could
have these two saints kind of go back
and forth on that topic. So you
basically define define the the topic
the context the saints go back and forth
and then we thought well wait a minute
how what about what if we appointed a
judge at the debate, right? What if what
if you could what if you could appoint a
judge? So you could have someone like
Thomas Aquinus could could actually
judge who he thinks won the debate. And
so this is something we're building in
right now is and we think this will be
interesting. You know, it'd be fun, but
we also think it'd be interesting for
research, right? Because I mean,
>> oh yeah,
>> I mean, with all that context available
for each of the saints, I mean, there
could be interesting observations,
right, in insights that happen just by
bouncing these these different ideas off
each other. And and so I that's another,
you know, facet of St. Chad I'm really
excited about. We we have some other,
you know, uh, features as well. I'll
just kind of, you know, quickly knock
them off. Voice mode, as I mentioned,
will be rolling out soon. So, you'll be
able to actually talk uh and natural
language like you do to um to to all the
major um apps that that'll be coming out
soon. We have a a learn mode which will
be specifically for education. And so,
this will be uh designed to help
teachers uh develop programming
curricula and then also for students.
And so, it'll be very similar to the
experience you'd have in like claude AI
and some of the other AI platforms. I
know Chachdi has as an education mode as
well. So, essentially it's it's it's me
it's not there to give you necessarily
this just you know a direct answer. It's
meant to help you kind of think through
the questions and arrive out the answer
on your own. So, I'm pretty excited
about I think I think there's a lot of
need for kind of Catholic AI in the
education space because I think they
know right now that a lot of their
students are using secular AIS and they
want to try and use a one that's uh it's
it's trying at least to be aligned. So,
I think that feature will be useful as
well. And Matthew, can you can you talk
a little bit about, you know, with
regards to, you know, Catholic students
using these secular LLMs, like the
importance of fidelity and what what
that looks like, um, visa v the, you
know, the other the other models.
>> Sure. I mean, um,
>> like what's at risk when when, you know,
students are on these b major secular,
you know, models and they're they're
asking questions and they can they can
receive what seems like a a good answer
but actually could be filled with errors
or, you know, lead them in the wrong
place.
>> Sure. I mean I mean I I you know I think
I I spoke about this earlier. I mean I
mean in large part this is an issue not
just for students. It's the same issue
for anybody, right? I mean if you ask if
you ask Chach a question and it gives
you an answer. Uh it may it may it may
do some reverse rag and and and check
the internet, right? Um 44 for sources
and if you active research mode it may
it may go and you know grab some sources
online but again you know it's hard work
because because then you get the answer
which may sound great but then you have
to look into all the sources right these
are different websites. You have to
bounce around to the websites and
evaluate them. Is this website, you
know, faithfully represented what the
church says or or not? I don't know. I I
find that kind of, you know, tedious and
and if and if you're writing, if you
have to write like a paper for school,
like you need to make sure your sources
are legit, right? And so spending time
going through all these sources and
question that that's a lot of work. So I
think, you know, one of the nice things
about magisti is all the sources are
credible, right? So they're either
magisterial or or they're they're very
notable and established Catholic
philosophical theological works. I mean,
we're we're pretty selective right now
uh about what we include inside of the
knowledge base. I mean, so when I say
Catholic theological and philosophical
works, I'm talking about like church
fathers and doctors of the church for
the most part. And then we're just
starting to introduce uh theological uh
journals in there as well. But these are
theological journals from um pontypical
universities and things like that. So
you know I think are uh you know
publications like kimono which which
Joseph rating you know founded with Hans
on both stars. So uh so in that in that
sense if you're a student and you ask me
a question you get sources you just
don't have to you don't have to
scrutinize the sources as much as you
would if you're using kind of a you know
secular and and that that's not even
touching on the propensity for
psychopancy and and hallucinations and
things which are just much more prone in
these other LMS.
And Matthew, can you can you talk to us
a little bit about the the team behind
the scenes that that's working on how
many how many people are working on on
Magisterium AI? What what makes them
special, you know, to just share with
our
>> I mean, we're a small team, very small
team, and it's uh it's a global team.
So, we have some team members in Africa,
we have some team members in in North
America, and then we have, you know,
team members in Europe. Um so so that
that's nice because you you um you
people from very different contexts and
uh and and and and a lot of the times
you know they're in touch with local
users who have very you know uh specific
asks about how they want the what kind
of features or how they want the the
product to develop. So um so that's been
useful and it's particularly because you
know ever since we launched the platform
we've always had to think globally which
has been a big challenge right I mean
when we launched it we recognized that
that the AI would well it was being used
all over the world and so and so that
meant that we had to make sure that the
user interface was translated into you
know into the language of the respective
you know regions that were used in the
world and we had also had to make sure
that we were trying to um you know get
uh ingest works which are particularly
relevant to those regions as well so
there was something of a local
experience And so um so anyways the team
has been very useful um you know and in
that respect and and and uh I humble I
mean that's one thing I love about our
team is I think this project requires a
a great deal of humility particularly
because we're doing a lot of um kind of
research and experimentation and so uh
sometimes you know uh we may propose
some kind of radical ideas and you know
and and so it takes a lot of like
patience and humility to and allow
people to to share those you know those
different approaches and then you know
also to have kind of the courage to let
them, you know, try things out and um
and and of course recognizing that of
course the enormity of what we're doing.
I mean, when you're when you're doing
something like representing church
teaching for people, I mean, I mean, it
it feels like an awesome responsibility.
And so, there's this big tension that
we've always kind of had in the company
as, you know, we have to make sure that
everything we do is is as safe as it
possibly can be safe. And that's meant
that we've moved slower than some other
companies in some respects because uh uh
we we don't want to risk hallucinations.
We don't want to lead someone astray.
And and this is certainly something as
I've traveled around and and spoken to
the various bishious conferences. This
has been a big sticking point for them
and and I think this is one of the
things they've appreciated about
particularly about Madison is that uh we
we do kind of the hard work. You know,
we do we do the we build the eval sets
and we we we go after digitizing you
know the work needs to be digitized even
sometimes when it hasn't been digitized.
we we'll we'll put that work in because
we recognize it's important to make sure
that we're we're providing the right
answers and and so you know uh one thing
I'll say I I talk about like you know
patience and humility but one thing I
have to say I mean I've been remarkable
it's been remarkable for me as as a CEO
of the company is is the is um is the
grit of the team I mean some of the
things we asked them to do especially in
the early days uh was just some tedious
stuff I mean I mean literally going and
copying and pasting you know text right
out and chunking it for our AI um So
digitizing, you know, the the patchway
of the church in the early days was
incredibly tedious. It was very
hands-on. Now, you know, we've been able
to develop more and more AI tools to
help facilitate that and vulgate
obviously been a big help. But I mean,
there were there were times I mean I
mean almost as say eight months where
they were just literally every day just
going and finding texts and running them
through translation engines or copying
and pasting and then chunking them for
and and so and and this is something
that not not just uh we didn't just hire
you know digital injust people. Some of
these these people worked at the
marketing team and things like that. So
they they just they jumped in because
they recognized especially in the early
days this this this knowledge base being
so limited in size was causing problems
and they recognized this is something
that it takes all hands on deck. We all
got to drop what we're doing and just
focus on this one issue. So I I
appreciate that because that was really
that was really grilling work and they
and they stuck with it even though it
wasn't part of their their brief.
>> That's very inspiring. And Matthew um
you mentioned you speaking at different
bishop's conferences. What has been the
response from the from the church in you
know whether the local you know the
local bishop or or you know all the way
up to you know being here in Rome and
and having contact with certain
cardinals and and members of the Holy
Sea.
>> Well I I think it's it surprised me when
I when I first and again I've I've been
doing this for you know almost two years
now. So, you know, it's it's changed a
bit the response, but I I will say even
from even from the early days,
there wasn't really a heated debate. I
mean, I have to say the first time I was
summoned to, you know, to a couple
bishious conferences. Summon's not the
right way to put it, but um when I
showed up there, I I was a little
worried. It might I was might be walking
into like a firing squad, you know, like
um because, you know, I you know, the AI
wasn't perfect, you know, and and we
knew we knew we we still had challenges
and and and I was worried that they may
say too big a risk and we should stop,
which which I was deeply sympathetic to
at the time. And I wrestled with myself.
I I again like I said the reason why I
just kept going is because I realized
that it's it's kind of a zero sum if if
we if they can't come to us they're
going to go to another AI it's just how
it is now right but uh but I was really
surprised I the most part the questions
started really around just what is this
technology explain it to me I I don't
understand it right how is this
different from what's come before so
that was kind of cool kind of a little
bit of factf finding and then as opposed
to them saying ah it's too risky you
know um I don't like it, right? It's not
human. They were more just curious, you
know, they're asking questions about as
it as a tool. So, I mean I mean, how far
can we go with this tool? I mean, which
which way is it good? Which way is it
not? So, that kind of curiosity gave me
gave me a lot of hope. I think I think
for the most part, most bishops did see
it. Something like the printing press,
right? Something that's useful and
doesn't doesn't seem like something the
church should ignore. It's it's too
useful a tool. I mean, they all they all
went to seminary. They all studied, you
know, and and they know how hard it is,
right, to go and find, you know, get
answers to certain questions. They've
all been the libraries and how to pull
books out of the stack. So I think they
all recognized that there's ways to make
that, you know, more process more
efficient. This is good. And I think
they also, you know, again, like this is
Pope Francis's, you know, uh, time when
he was pope and and he talked a lot
about reaching the peripheries. And I
think all the bishops recognized that we
have to do a better job of ensuring
that, you know, Catholic wisdom and
insight makes its way to the peripheries
in particular, right? And it's distilled
so that they can understand it. And, uh,
and they also knew that there are
limited priests and there's there's
limited catechists. And so this is a
problem which is you know extremely
difficult to solve and I think so any
kind of tool that can maybe will help us
on this has to be at least explored. So,
so that's just a long way of saying gen
I generally think there were they were
very open and and then you know over the
course of you know a couple years there
was more and more enthusiasm there was
still some obviously some concern about
the technology generally in society and
that's something we would we we talk a
lot about is where is this technology
headed what are the likely impacts on on
civilization what is the unique role of
the church in this and you know I
provide whatever insights I could uh I'm
no expert in that um but but I think for
the most part I think that they know
that AI is here to stay and it's
something that the church um has to has
to invest in and we and we should try to
to be a leader in this technology in in
so far as we can.
>> That's very inspiring. And um Matthew, I
guess final question is um you know Pope
Leo the 14th has uh spoken quite a bit
about uh artificial intelligence um and
it looks like you know in the coming
months we'll most likely hear that he
has an encyclical speaking on this
topic. Uh do you have any insight if
he's a Magisterium Mayi user?
>> I I doubt it. I doubt it. Um, you know,
he's he is one of those rare people, I
think, on Earth, right? He's got enough
he's got enough uh saved upstairs. I
don't think he has to he has to use an
LLM. Um, but I mean I mean he's I yeah,
I think, you know, he's I I'm honestly
very happy that he recognizes the the
import of the technology and and I do
think it'll be a central focus of his
pontificate, which is good because the
technology is going to, you know, re
reshape human civilization like no other
technology has before. You know, I think
it'll be it'll be the the import of it
will be far far greater than the
industrial revolution, which is
difficult to like conceive of
and and I think we're certainly going to
need someone um like Pope Leo to help
shepherd us through this transition.
But my my hope for him
when it comes to this kind of technology
is is that and I think he will like I I
hope he will is just is to focus on the
fundamentals, right? is is to not is not
get distracted by people who who want
him to opine on the ethics of the
technology or how it's or you know it it
the way that it's being you know
practically applied by this lab is that
good or is that bad. I'm not saying that
there's not use in the church kind of
being on record when it comes to e
ethics of AI and how it's practically
used in the world. I mean obviously
right I mean obviously that the church
has to safeguard um the human person and
in any ways that the technology seems to
be impeding you know human dignity the
church has to speak out but but I think
you know if all if all the church is
doing is just reacting all the time I I
think that that's um that could be a big
problem because the techn is moving at
at such a quick pace you know uh you'll
spend all all day reacting and I and I
think what's needed more from the church
than anything else is is to help does
know where to direct the technology like
I mean you know like even when
governments are coming up with
regulations for the technology I mean
they're saying the technology should be
used like this and it shouldn't be used
like that I mean that that's a
termination of when it should be used
and when it shouldn't be is based on a
credential judgment which is based on
what right and I and I that you would
think that's based upon some you know
some fundamental insights in the human
condition but also on some understanding
of where this technology should be
leading humanity right what kind of a
world and That's where I think the pope
can add unique value cuz I I I think for
most of us have a hard time envisioning
what the world's going to look like and
well I mean and maybe in some ways it's
very easy in the sense because Hollywood
has shown us all kinds of ways the world
this could play out but most of them
seem like they're fairly doomerist right
I mean like most of what Hollywood has
shown us the future is going to look
like I think when it comes to technology
human beings it doesn't look good it
looks like post-apocalyptic and so and I
think that we're we're supposed to be
people of hope and so if that's how
we're g if that's how we're going to
proceed
I really worry I really worry about uh
how this is going to play out. Like I I
I think we we need to have a clear
understanding of what the city of God
looks like. And as you know, as as he's
an Augustinian, I hope what he can do is
help remind us of what the city of God
looks like and and and can help uh
encourage us to to focus more on
building that. And I think that in large
part that just starts with just
understanding what is the purpose of the
human being, right? Um what is our what
is what is our purpose? what should we
be doing with our lives? What matters in
in life? And then what kind of
civilization do we need you know built
up around us in order to help you know
facilitate human flourishing basically
right so if if the church is is the is
the leading expert in the human
condition which I believe that it is has
been studying the human conditioning
long continuously longer than any
organization on earth what we need from
the church right now is is for them to
help us understand what what uh a future
civilization which is focusing and
flourishing practically looks like. What
what does day-to-day life look like?
what is the right relationship of AI and
robots in that new world, right? What
things should robots be doing? What
things shouldn't robots be doing? And
the same same goes same goes for AI. So,
if they can help us get clear about, as
Cardinal Collins used to say to me, you
know, uh if you know where you're going,
we're likely to get there. If they can
help us get clear about where we're
supposed to be going, then I think we
can work backwards and then we can make
sure that the regulations we're
proposing or the ethics, the ethical
frameworks we're developing for AI are
properly aligned towards towards an end.
And that and in some ways that that
that's good because once we understand
that end and we know that we have the
right regulations and and ethical
frameworks in place, we can be excited.
We can be hopeful about the future we're
building, right? Because we all know
it's better than than where we are now
and our kids will be better off if we
put in the work. And so this I feel like
this is something that this pope in
particular, especially being an
Augustinian, is is really poised um to
add a lot of value in. And I and I hope
he spends more time in that than than
the whole reacting to the technology.
Well, that would that would be very very
um inspiring and is deeply deeply
needed. Um well, Matthew, thank you so
much uh for sitting down with me and
sharing some of this uh the story behind
LongBid behind Majesty Mayi and on the
journey and uh we'll be in touch then
tomorrow for uh for a debrief on
Catholic AI.
>> Thanks very much, Ben.